Guide to the Chris Kraus Papers MSS.442
Fales Library and Special Collections
Chris Kraus Papers
1975-2015
Fales Library and Special Collections
Kraus, Chris, 1963-
MSS.442
54 Linear Feet in 68 manuscript boxes, 19 record cartons, 4 half manuscript boxes, 7 flat boxes, 1 media box, and 3 flat file folders
215 Reels in 170 Super 8 reels and 45 16mm reels
86 audiocassettes in 68 compact audio cassettes, 14 DAT cassettes, and 4 micro-cassettes
68 videocassettes in 19 VHS cassettes, 42 UMatic cassettes, 3 Betacam cassettes, 1 Betamax cassette, 2 Hi-8 cassettes, and 1 Mini-DV cassette
13 videodiscs (dvd)
40 Reels in 40 1/4" audio reels
2 videoreels (1 inch)
8.6 Gigabytes in 4508 computer files
5.3 Gigabytes in 23 email archives containing 74,164 messages
44 video disc (dvd) images
3 audio files
Chris Kraus (born 1955) is an American writer, art critic, editor, filmmaker, writing instructor, playwright, and theatre director. She is best known for her autobiographical novel, I Love Dick. Her other novels include Aliens & Anorexia and Torpor, and her non-fiction writing includes the collections Video Green: Los Angeles Art and the Triumph of Nothingness and Where Art Belongs, as well as the biography After Kathy Acker. Her films include The Golden Bowl or Repression and Gravity & Grace. The Chris Kraus Papers date from 1975 to 2015 and document Kraus's career as a writer, art critic, editor, filmmaker, playwright, and theatre director. The collection consists of paper, audiovisual, and born-digital material and includes drafts of Kraus's critical writing and books, audiovisual material documenting all stages of production for her films, research materials for her writing, correspondence with friends and collaborators, and Kraus' personal diaries.
Biographical note
Chris Kraus (born 1955) is an American writer, art critic, editor, filmmaker, writing instructor, playwright, and theatre director. She is best known for her autobiographical novel, I Love Dick. From the late 1970s to the early 1980s, she worked in New York City as a playwright and theatre director. She wrote and directed the plays Disparate Action/Desperate Action and Readings from the Diaries of Hugo Ball, and co-wrote I Talked about God with Antonin Artaud with Sylvère Lotringer. They later collaborated on the film How to Shoot a Crime. Kraus was married to Lotringer from the late 1980s through the late 1990s. While working in theatre in the early 1980s, Kraus began to write and produce short films. These include The Golden Bowl or Repression and Gravity and Grace. In 1990, she started as co-editor with Lotringer at Semiotext(e), a journal and small publishing house he founded 1974, and she started the Native Agents Series there at the time. At the time of this writing (2019), Kraus was still co-editor at Semiotext(e). In the late 1990s, she moved to Los Angeles, California and began focusing on art criticism, fiction writing, and teaching. Some of her notable works include the autobiographical novels I Love Dick, Aliens & Anorexia, and Summer of Hate; the non-fiction collections Video Green: Los Angeles Art and the Triumph of Nothingness and Where Art Belongs; and the biography After Kathy Acker.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection received from Chris Kraus in two installments in October 2015; the accession numbers associated with these donations are 2015.442.001 and 2015.442.002. In March 2016, an accretion was added; the accession number associated with this donation is 2016.015. In February and June 2017 two small accretions were added; the accession numbers associated with these donations are 2017.036 and 2018.095.
Related Materials
For more information on Kraus's work at Semiotext(e), see the Sylvère Lotringer Papers and Semiotext(e) Archive (MSS 221).
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in five series: Series I. Writing, Series II. Film, Series III. Diaries, Series IV. Correspondence, and Series V. The Chance Event.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions, with the exception of Series III. Diaries, and email and select correspondence in Series IV. Correspondence which require donor permission to access. Please contact the Fales Library & Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2596.
Scope and Contents
The Chris Kraus Papers document Kraus's career as a writer, art critic, editor, filmmaker, writing instructor, playwright, and theatre director. The collection dates from 1975 through 2015 and contains paper, born-digital, and audiovisual materials documenting her work through this time. These materials include drafts of Kraus's plays, films, novels, and critical writings; research materials used in her work; video, audio, and film recordings for her films; correspondence with friends and collaborators; and Kraus's personal diaries. Well documented in the collection is her work as a writer of fiction and non-fiction, and as a filmmaker. The collection includes her autobiographical novels I Love Dick, Torpor, and Summer of Hate. Kraus's work on these novels is documented through paper and born-digital material, including diary entries regarding experiences that served as the basis for the novels, notes and drafts, research and source materials, galley proofs, publicity and reviews, and correspondence regarding all aspects of the creative process. Similar material for her critical art writing and films is included in the collection, particularly the collections of her critical writing, Video Green: Los Angeles Art and the Triumph of Nothingness and Where Art Belongs; her biography After Kathy Acker; and her films Golden Bowl or Repression and Gravity and Grace. Also included in the collection are paper and born-digital typescripts, notes, and publicity materials for her plays and theatre work, as well as video, audio, and film recordings of these performances. Also in the collection are correspondence, drafts, and notes documenting Kraus's work as a co-editor at Semiotext(e) and material from The Chance Event, a three day event curated by Kraus in Nevada in 1996 that focused on philosophy, music, and culture.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
American fiction -- 20th century.; Audiovisual materials.; Film (material by form); Independent filmmakers -- United States.; Art criticism.; Scripts (documents); Diaries; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Videocassettes.; Audiocassettes.; Autobiographical fiction.; Women novelists, American.; Independent films -- Production and direction -- United States.; Women motion picture producers and directors -- United States.; Women periodical editors.; Motion pictures and directors -- United States; Periodical editors; Semiotexte
- Series I. Writing, 1977-2015; 29.5 Linear Feet in 48 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 5 record cartons, 5 flat boxes, 1 media box, and 2 flat file folders; 21 videocassettes in 2 Hi-8 cassettes, 6 VHS cassettes, 1 Mini-DV cassette, and 12 UMatic cassettes; 6 videodiscs (dvd); 8 audiocassettes; 2 film reels in 2 Super 8 reels; 6.6 Gigabytes in 4082 computer files; 36 video disc (dvd) images; 3 audio files
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by format of material and then by title of work. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of titles, with some titles listed individually when they consist of a large amount of material.
  Scope and Contents
  This series represents Kraus's work as a fiction writer, art critic, playwright, theatre director, editor, and creative writing instructor. The material dates from 1974 through 2015. Included in this series are paper and born-digital versions of material related to Kraus's work as an author, teacher, and editor at Semiotext(e); audio and video recordings of performances of her work; and writing about Kraus. Materials related to Kraus's writings include drafts, research materials, notes, publicity materials, reviews, and correspondence. The bulk of the series documents Kraus's autobiographical novels and her critical writing on art and includes paper and born-digital materials. Kraus's books documented in this series include I Love Dick, Torpor, Summer of Hate, Aliens & Anorexia, After Kathy Acker, Video Green: Los Angeles Art and the Triumph of Nothingness, and Where Art Belongs. This material consists of paper and born-digital drafts, proofs, published books and magazines, newspaper and magazine clippings, notes, photographs, posters, flyers, correspondence, and audiovisual material. In addition, the I Love Dick material includes scripts of Longing Lasts Longer, a 1998 play based on I Love Dick, as well as correspondence regarding its production, and photographs and video recordings of the performance. Also included in this section are some of Kraus and Lotringer's notebooks and letters to Dick used in the creation of the book, and fan mail sent to Kraus after the publication of the book. Kraus's art writing includes critical writing on artists and their exhibitions in the United States and Europe, and catalog essays for exhibitions. This work is documented through paper and born-digital drafts, notes, published books and magazines, as well as magazine and newspaper clippings. Research materials include photocopies and clippings of critical writings by others, exhibit catalogs, and correspondence with artists and editors. Kraus's essays on topics other than art and her short stories are also included in this series.
  This series also documents Kraus's theatre work in New York City in the 1970s and 1980s, including Readings from the Diaries of Hugo Ball, Disparate Action/Desperate Action, and collaborations with Sylvère Lotringer on the works of Antonin Artaud. This material also documents Kraus's theatre workshops with labor unions and other groups in New York City. The theatre material includes video and audio recordings of Readings from the Diaries of Hugo Ball, I Talked about God with Antonin Artaud, an untitled performance of Artaud's work at Columbia University, and audio recordings of workshops Kraus held with labor union members.
  Also included in this series are materials related to interviews conducted with and by Kraus, writing about her work, awards and grants she received, her speaking engagements, her work as a teacher, her work as an editor at Semiotext(e), and photographs. The interviews include those conducted by Kraus with Penny Arcade and Christopher Isherwood, and an interview conducted by Gary Indiana with Kraus. Writing about Kraus includes reviews of her work, as well as critical interpretations of her writings. The photographs consist of photographs of Kraus used for publicity materials and of events at which she appeared. The material related to speaking engagements includes posters, flyers, and catalogs for the events as well as correspondence regarding planning for the events. The teaching material documents Kraus's work at the European Graduate School and includes syllabi; correspondence regarding the planning of the classes; diary entries about teaching and the class locations; and notes on what the focus of the classes should be, as well as ideas for projects and readings for the students. Material documenting Kraus's work as an editor at Semiotext(e) includes born-digital correspondence, drafts, and notes regarding publication of works in Semiotext(e)'s Native Agents series as well as their general publishing areas.
  - Art Writing -- After Kathy Acker, 2013-2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_1)
  - Art Writing -- A - C, 1988-2015 (Box 13, Folder 1-12, Box 14, Box 17, Folder 1-10, Box 18, Folder 1-7, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_31)
  - Art Writing -- D - J, 2002-2015 (Box 18, Folder 8-9, Box 19, Folder 1-9, Box 20, Folder 1, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_29)
  - Art Writing -- K - N, 1999-2015 (Box 21, Folder 2-8, Box 22, Folder 1-7, Box 23, Folder 1-9, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 2, Folder 6, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_28)
  - Art Writing -- P - S, 1996-2015 (Box 23, Folder 10-11, Box 24, Folder 1-17, Box 25, Folder 1-3, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_32)
  - Art Writing -- T - Y, 2005-2015 (Box 25, Folder 4-10, Box 26, Folder 6, Box 27, Folder 1-3, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_30)
  - Art Writing -- Video Green: Los Angeles Art and the Triumph of Nothingness, 1996-2015 (Box 48, Folder 1-8, Box 49, Folder 1-7, Box 50, Box 51, Box 57, Folder 7, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_13)
  - Art Writing -- Where Art Belongs, 2006-2015 (Box 15, Folder 1-10, Box 16, Folder 1-11, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_14)
  - Awards and Grants, 1985-2015 (Box 32, Folder 10-11, Box 57, Folder 8-10, Folder 22, Box 79, Folder 7, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_4)
  - Curricula Vitae, 1991-2015 (Box 57, Folder 23, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_3)
  - Essays and Short Stories, 1978-2015; 1 videodisc (dvd); 2 videocassettes (vhs) (Box 28, Folder 1-14, Box 29, Box 30, Folder 1-9, Box 31, Folder 1-19, Box 60, Box 92, Folder 1, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_12)
  - Fiction -- Aliens & Anorexia, 1996-2015 (Box 40, Folder 7-10, Box 41, Folder 1-11, Box 42, Folder 1-13, Box 43, Folder 1-2, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 1, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_2)
  - Fiction -- I Love Dick, 1994-2015; 4 videocassettes in 2 Hi-8 cassettes, 2 VHS cassettes (Box 51, Folder 8-10, Box 52, Folder 1-8, Box 53, Folder 1-9, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Folder 1-5, Box 57, Folder 1-2, Box 60, Box 88, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_5)
  - Fiction -- Summer of Hate, 2003-2015; 1 videocassettes (minidv) (Box 43, Folder 3-7, Box 44, Folder 1-8, Box 45, Folder 1-7, Box 46, Box 47, Folder 1-6, Box 57, Folder 5, Box 88, Box 92, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 8, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_9)
  - Fiction -- Torpor, 1997-2015; 1 audiocassette (Box 36, Folder 6-13, Box 37, Folder 1-9, Box 38, Folder 1-12, Box 39, Folder 1-7, Box 40, Folder 1-6, Box 57, Folder 6, Box 85, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_11)
  - Interviews, 1982-2015; 7 videocassettes in 1 VHS cassette, 4 UMatic cassettes; 2 audiocassettes (Box 33, Folder 12-14, Box 34, Folder 10-16, Box 35, Folder 1-14, Box 36, Folder 1-5, Box 57, Folder 11-12, Box 60, Box 74, Box 80, Folder 3, Box 85, Box 92, Folder 3-4, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_6)
  - Photographs, 1978-2015 (Box 33, Folder 6-11, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_7)
  - Semiotext(e) Files, 1997-2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_26)
  - Speaking Engagements, 1980-2015 (Box 34, Folder 2-7, Box 57, Folder 24, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 7, Box Shared Fales 020, Folder 8, Flat-file-folder 5, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_8)
  - Teaching Files, 2007-2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_10)
  - Theatre -- B - H, 1979-1982; 1 audiocassette (Box 58, Folder 7-15, Box 79, Folder 3, Box 75, Folder 1-4, Box 85)
  - Theatre -- I Talked about God with Antonin Artaud -- Paper and Audiovisual Materials, 1985-2011; 1 audiocassette; 3 videodiscs (dvd) (Box 32, Folder 7-8, Box 75, Folder 5-6, Box 86, Box Electronic Records, Item FA_MSS_442_ER_48)
  - Theatre -- J - Po, 1981-1988; 1 audiocassette; 2 film reels 2 Super 8 film reels (Box 32, Folder 1-3, Box 73, Box 85, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 10)
  - Theatre -- Punch-Out -- Digitized Audio, undated; cuid7128 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid7128, Box 86, Cassette mss.442.cuid7128)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    1/8" audiocassette, 49 min.
  - Theatre -- Punch-Out -- Paper Materials, 1980-1981 (Box 32, Folder 4-6, Box 57, Folder 20-21, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 9)
  - Theatre -- Readings from the Diaries of Hugo Ball, 1983-2011; 5 videocassettes in 1 VHS cassette, 4 UMatic cassettes; 2 videodiscs (dvd); 1 audiocassette (Box 57, Folder 25-27, Box 58, Folder 1-6, Box 60, Box 71, Box 85, Flat-file-folder 2, Box Electronic Records, Item FA_MSS_442_ER_52)
  - Theatre -- Things Happen But They Change -- Digitized Audio, undated; cuid7127 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid7127, Box 86, Cassette mss.442.cuid7127)
    1/8" audiocassette, 39 min.
  - Theatre -- Things Happen But They Change -- Paper Materials, 1981 (Box 33, Folder 4-5)
  - Theatre -- Unidentified Antonin Artaud Performance at Columbia University [1 of 3] -- Digitized Video, 1985; cuid7124 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid7124, Box 70, Cassette mss.442.cuid7124)
    Housing annotations read: David Rattray
    Format: 3/4" Umatic, Duration: 61 min.
  - Theatre -- Unidentified Antonin Artaud Performance at Columbia University [2 of 3] -- Digitized Video, 1985; cuid7125 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid7125, Box 70, Cassette mss.442.cuid7125)
    Format: 3/4" Umatic, Duration: 44 min.
  - Theatre -- Unidentified Antonin Artaud Performance at Columbia University [3 of 3] -- Digitized Video, 1986; cuid7126 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid7126, Box 70, Cassette mss.442.cuid7126)
    Format: 3/4" Umatic [Master], Duration: 52 min.
  - Writing about Kraus, 1982-2015 (Box 32, Folder 12-13, Box 33, Folder 1-3, Box 34, Folder 8-9, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_15)
- Series II. Films, 1980-2015; 24 Linear Feet in 15 record cartons, 10 manuscript boxes, 7 flat boxes, 1 media box, and 1 flat file folder; 77 audiocassettes in 60 compact audio cassettes, 14 DAT cassettes, and 3 micro-cassettes; 45 videocassettes in 11 VHS cassettes, 30 Umatic cassettes, 3 Betacam cassettes, 1 Betamax cassette; 7 videodiscs (dvd); 40 Reels in 40 1/4" audio reels; 2 videoreels (1 inch); 213 film reels in 45 16 mm reels and 168 Super 8 reels; 1.7 Gigabytes in 383 computer files; 8 video disc (dvd) images
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by title of work or by format of material.
  This series contains paper, born-digital, and audiovisual material documenting Kraus's career as a filmmaker from the early 1980s through the mid 1990s. The series dates from 1980-2015 and includes scripts, notes, publicity materials, correspondence, film, video, and audio recordings. The bulk of this series consists of materials for Gravity and Grace, The Golden Bowl or Repression, and How to Shoot a Crime. The film, video, and audio recordings in this series document all stages of production of the films and include final prints used for screenings. There are some audiovisual materials that have not been identified as belonging to any specific film; in these cases titles from the media label has been retained. The paper and born-digital material in this series includes finished and draft scripts, production materials, correspondence, and press material. The production materials include notes, receipts, grant applications, crew lists and resumes, and correspondence regarding aspects of production. Topics in the correspondence include issues with filming locations, screenings, as well as funding for the film. Press materials include reviews, stationery, postcards, posters, and stickers. Photographs include production stills and candids taken during production. Other films documented in this series include Sadness at Leaving, Traveling at Night, Voyage to Rodez, Foolproof Illusion, and In Order to Pass. This series also documents Kraus's participation in film exhibitions and conferences through paper and born-digital correspondence, exhibition catalogs, and posters.
  - 6 + 6, undated; 1 videocassettes (u-matic) (Box 101, U-matic 442_0043)
  - Armand Schwermer, undated; 1 audiocassette in one compact cassette. (Box 97, Audiocassette 442_0032)
  - Arnette the Absolute, 1990-1991 (Box 81, Folder 3-5, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_35)
  - Bonsai, 1993 (Box 81, Folder 6)
  - Cafeteria hallway voiceover, undated (Box 97, Vhs 442_0025)
  - Cattle auction, untitled (Box 97, Vhs 442_0020)
  - Classroom scene, undated (Box 97, Quarter inch audio reel 442_0029)
  - Compilation of films, undated (Box 96, U-matic 442_0003)
  - Dead Sky Scrawl, Undated (Box 81, Folder 7-9)
  - The Department, Undated; 1 audiocassette (Box 85)
  - Film Exhibitions, 1992-2015 (Box 79, Folder 16-19, Box 80, Folder 1-2, Box Shared Fales 028, Folder 4, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_442_ER_16)
  - Film Reviews, 1982-2015 (Box 80, Folder 7-13, Box 81, Folder 1-2)
  - Foolproof Illusion -- "Artaud Dungeon Scenes" [1 of 2] -- Digitized Video, Undated; cuid7003 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid7003, Box 71, Cassette mss.442.cuid7003)
    Housing annotations read: "Artaud Dungeon Scenes; Session 1 - Total Garbage; Marat/Sade + Terry's worm speech in midshot; bandage knife + blood"
    Format: 3/4" umatic, Duration: 22 min.
  - Foolproof Illusion -- Paper and Video Materials, 1986; 1 videocassettes (vhs); 2 videodiscs (dvd) (Box 60, Box 83, Folder 5, Box Electronic Records, File FA_MSS_442_ER_41)
  - Foolproof Illusion -- Video, 1987; cuid6993 (Box 96, Cassette MSS.442.cuid6993)
    3/4" Umatic, 20 min.
  - Foolproof Illusion -- Snow Scene -- Nontransferable Video, 1986; cuid6999 (Box 71, Cassette MSS.442.cuid6999)
    Housing annotations read: "Chris Kraus as Suzan Cooper; Camera: Bart Friedman; Media Bus, Saugerties NY, February 1986. Includes Rodez titles and Terrorist credits"
    Format: 3/4" Umatic, Duration: 15 min.
  - The Golden Bowl or Repression -- 16mm Film Reel, 1984-1988; cuid6292 (Box Shared Fales 048, Reel 6292A, Box Shared Fales 049, Reel 6292D, Box Shared Fales 061, Reel 6292B, 6292C, Box Shared Fales 060, Reel cuid6292)
    16mm film [Print], Sound, Color, 12 min. 30 sec.
  - The Golden Bowl or Repression -- Digitized Video, 1984-1988; cuid6293 (Box Electronic Records, File MSS.442.cuid6293, Box 70, Box 97, Vhs 442_0023)
    3/4" Umatic [Master], 13 min.
  - The Golden Bowl or Repression -- Paper and Audiovisual Materials, 1984-2011; 9 audiocassettes; 29 film reels in 3 16mm film reels, 26 Super 8 film reels; 2 videocassettes 1 UMatic, 1 VHS; 1 reel in 1 1/4" audio reel; 4 videodiscs (dvd) (Box 60, Box 61, Box 62, Box 66, Box 85, Box 82, Folder 9-12, Box 83, Folder 1-3, Box Electronic Records, File FA_MSS_442_ER_36, Box 97)